Nathaniel Alexander Owings Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Nathaniel Alexander Owings Papers 1911-1983 1960-1980
MSS75863
Owings, Nathaniel Alexander, 1903-
28,300 items
64 containers plus 12 oversize
29.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Architect and engineer. Correspondence, journals. memoranda, minutes and reports, drafts of speeches and writings, legal and financial papers, subject file, biographical material, poetry, notes, appointment calendars, charts, graphs, diagrams, clippings, printed matter, photographs, scrapbooks, and other material chiefly dating from 1960 to 1980, documenting Owings's career as a founding partner of the architectural firm, Skidmore, Owings & Merrill, as chairman of public commissions responsible for the redesign of Pennsylvania Avenue in Washington, D.C., as a member of various commissions relating to conservation, preservation, and redevelopment in California, and as an author of works on architecture and city planning.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, Ansel, 1902-1984--Correspondence.; Bechtel, Stephen Davison, 1925- --Correspondence.; Brown, Jerry, 1938- --Correspondence.; Eckardt, Wolf von, 1918- --Correspondence.; Goldberg, Arthur J., 1908-1990--Correspondence.; Johnson, Lady Bird, 1912-2007--Correspondence.; Moses, Robert, 1888-1981--Correspondence.; Moynihan, Daniel P. (Daniel Patrick), 1927-2003--Correspondence.; Owings, Nathaniel Alexander, 1903-1984.; Owings, Nathaniel Alexander, 1903-1984. American aesthetic.; Owings, Nathaniel Alexander, 1903-1984. Spaces in between.; Quesada, Elwood R. (Elwood Richard), 1904-1993--Correspondence.; Rockefeller, David, 1915-2017--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Nicholas, 1893-1982--Correspondence.; Stegner, Wallace, 1909-1993--Correspondence.; Udall, Stewart L.--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Institute of Architects.; California. Advisory Committee on a Master Plan for Scenic Highways.; Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation.; President's Council on Pennsylvania Avenue (U.S.); Skidmore, Owings & Merrill.
Subjects
Architectural firms.; Architecture--Awards--United States.; Architecture--United States.; City planning--California.; City planning--United States.; City planning--Washington (D.C.); Conservation of natural resources--California.; Historic preservation--California.; Hopi Indians.; Kachina dolls.; Monterey Peninsula (Calif.); Roadside improvement--California.; Urban beautification--United States.
Places
Pennsylvania Avenue (Washington, D.C.)
Occupations
Architects.; Engineers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Nathaniel Alexander Owings, architect and engineer, were given to the Library of Congress by Owings in 1977. Additions were given in 1980, 1983, and 1984.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Recorded tapes have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. Photographic material has been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Nathaniel Alexander Owings Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Nathaniel Alexander Owings are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1903, Feb. 5 Born, Indianapolis, Ind.
1921 1922 Student, University of Illinois, Urbana, Ill.
1927 B.S., Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1931 Married Emily Otis (divorced 1953)
1936 1984 Founding partner, Skidmore, Owings, & Merrill
1948 1951 Chairman, Chicago Planning Commission, Chicago, Ill.
1954 Married Margaret Wentworth
1962 1964 Chairman, President's Advisory Council on Pennsylvania Avenue, Washington, D.C.
1964 1973 Chairman, President's Temporary Commission on Pennsylvania Avenue, Washington, D.C.
1967 1970 Chairman, Control Urban Design Concept Team for Interstate Highway System, Baltimore, Md.
1969 Published The American Aesthetic (New York: Harper & Row. 198 pp.)
1970 1972 Chairman, Advisory Board on National Parks, Historic Sites, Buildings, and Monuments
1973 Published The Spaces in Between: An Architect's Journey (Boston: Houghton Mifflin. 303 pp.)
1983 Awarded the American Institute of Architects' Gold Medal
1984, June 13 Died, Santa Fe, N.Mex.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Nathaniel Alexander Owings (1903-1984) span the years 1911 to 1983, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1960-1980. The papers pertain to Owings's business, public, and personal affairs, documenting his career as a founding partner of the architectural firm Skidmore, Owings and Merrill (1936-1983); as chairman of several public commissions responsible for the redesign of Pennsylvania Avenue in Washington, D.C.; as a member of various commissions relating to conservation, preservation, and redevelopment in California; and as an author whose articles and books reflect his concern with both the aesthetic and practical applications of architecture in contemporary life. The collection includes correspondence, memoranda, journals, drafts of speeches and writings, notes, charts, graphs, diagrams, drawings, poetry, clippings, photographs, printed matter, and other material. The collection is organized in seven series: Correspondence, Office File, Subject File, Speeches and Writings File, Miscellany, Addition, and Oversize.
The Correspondence series, 1939-1977, contains Owings's incoming and outgoing correspondence and appended material reflecting his interests as architect, businessman, conservationist, and civic-minded citizen Although the series contains business papers pertaining to his role as a partner in the firm of Skidmore, Owings, and Merrill, the major portion consists of personal correspondence relating to his many other activities and interests. Correspondents include Ansel Adams, Stephen Davison Bechtel, Jerry Brown, Wolf von Eckardt, Arthur J. Goldberg, Lady Bird Johnson, Robert Moses, Daniel P. Moynihan, Elwood R. Quesada, David Rockefeller, Nicholas Roosevelt, Wallace Stegner, and Stewart L. Udall.
The Office File, 1954-1969, consists mostly of correspondence and memoranda relating to business concerns in the offices of Skidmore, Owings, and Merrill. The reading file consists of copies of Owings's outgoing letters and memoranda arranged chronologically. Records included in the corporate memoranda and general office files provide detailed documentation of the firm's internal operations. The former includes memoranda exchanged between secretaries and executives at the San Francisco home office with their counterparts in field offices, as well as memoranda circulated within the San Francisco office.
The Subject File, 1934-1977, documents many facets of Owings's business and personal life. The file contains information relating to his work on various committees and commissions including the California Advisory Committee on a Master Plan for State Scenic Highways, the Monterey Coast Master Plan, and various organizations relating to the redevelopment of Pennsylvania Avenue in Washington, D.C. Owings was appointed chairman of the President's Advisory Council on Pennsylvania Avenue by John F. Kennedy and later occupied the same position of its successor organization, the President's Temporary Commission on Pennsylvania Avenue. These organizations were charged, through remodeling and development, to redefine the area of Pennsylvania Avenue that connects the White House with the Capitol and, by so doing, bring it more in accord with the design of the original city plan by Pierre Charles L'Enfant.
The Speeches and Writings File, 1944-1977, reflects Owings's interest in numerous architectural and urban planning topics. The series contains early speeches and writings relating to specific architectural problems, later works concerning broader topics such as urban planning and architectural theory, and drafts, production materials, and correspondence relating to his two books The American Aesthetic (1969) and The Spaces in Between: An Architect's Journey (1973).
The Miscellany, 1911-1976, series contains a wide variety of material, such as appointment calendars, bills and receipts, postcards, and scrapbooks. Scrapbooks contain correspondence, clippings, and photographs.
The Addition consists of correspondence received and sent, biographical material, speeches and writings, legal and financial papers, minutes and reports, photographs, printed matter, and other material. Correspondence in the Addition is chiefly personal and contains a large segment relating to Owings's winning the American Institute of Architects' Gold Medal in 1983. Other topics of interest include the Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation, including Owings's letter of resignation to President Ronald Reagan, and his extensive collection of kachina dolls made by Hopi Indians. A miscellany file contains a copy of Owings's speech at the American Institute of Architects Gold Medal dinner in 1983. Also of interest are writings and other material relating to the Hopi Indians and a draft of an article, "Back to Earth," by Daniel P. Moynihan.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in seven series:
Correspondence, 1939-1977
Office File, 1954-1969
Subject File, 1934-1977
Speeches and Writings File, 1944-1977
Miscellany, 1911-1976
Addition, 1929-1983
Oversize, 1936-1975
Container List
- Correspondence, 1939-1977 (Box 1-6)
  Letters received, copies of letters sent, memoranda, telegrams, and miscellaneous items.
  The original reverse chronological filing order has been maintained.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - 1961-1962, (3 folders)
    - 1963-1965
      - A-O, (2 folders)
      - P-Z (Box 2)
  - Personal
    - 1939, Apr. 1948-June 1956, (3 folders)
    - July 1956-Dec. 1958, (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1959-1960, (5 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1961-1975, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1976-1977, undated, (3 folders) (Box 6)
- Office File, 1954-1969 (Box 6-10)
  Letters received, copies of letters sent, memoranda, telephone messages, telegrams, and miscellaneous items.
  Arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Chronological reading file (Box 6)
    - 1963-1964, (3 folders)
    - 1965-1966, (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - Corporate memoranda (Box 8)
    - Interoffice
      - General file
        - 1956-1969, (2 folders)
      - Chicago office
        - 1954-1960
        - 1965-1969 (Box 9)
      - New York office
        - 1954-1960
        - 1965-1969
      - Portland office
        - 1954-1959
        - 1965-1967
    - Intraoffice (San Francisco office) (Box 10)
      - 1954-1960
      - 1965-1968
  - General office file, 1955-1958, (2 folders)
  - Telephone messages
- Subject File, 1934-1977 (Box 11-44)
  Letters received, copies of letters sent, printed matter, memoranda, financial and legal papers, telegrams, reports, architectural diagrams, and miscellaneous items.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Adlai Stevenson Memorial Fund See Container 43, Stevenson (Adlai) Memorial Fund (Box 11)
  - Air Force Academy and Chapel, Colorado Springs, Colo.
  - Alexander, Robert E.
  - American Institute of Architects
    - California Council
      - Convention
      - Public Works Committee
      - Transportation Committee
    - Committee on Architectural Museum
    - Committee on Education
    - Convention, 1967
    - Fellowships
    - Fund-raising (Box 12)
    - General file
      - 1959-1967, (4 folders)
      - 1968-1972 (Box 13)
    - Headquarters Committee
    - Human Resources Council
    - Northern California chapter
  - American Academy in Rome, Rome, Italy
    - 1957-1960
    - 1961-1977, (5 folders) (Box 14)
  - American Film Institute (Box 15)
  - Association for Applied Solar Energy
  - Ball State University, Muncie, Ind.
  - Baltimore, Md.
    - Expense reports
    - Highway construction
      - Contract
      - Correspondence, 1966-1971, (2 folders)
      - Minutes of meetings
      - Miscellany (Box 16)
      - Printed matter
    - Miscellany
  - Boy Scouts of America
  - California
    - Advisory Committee on a Master Plan for State Scenic Highways
      - Agenda and minutes
      - Correspondence, 1964-1967
      - Miscellany (Box 17)
      - Monterey County
      - Printed matter, (4 folders)
      - Printed matter, (1 folder) (Box 18)
      - Redwoods
      - Scenic highway corridors
      - Senate bill no. 1467
      - Senate Fact Finding Committee
    - Big Sur National Park proposal
    - California Roadside Council, 1963-1970
    - California Tomorrow (Box 19)
      - Articles of incorporation and bylaws
      - Correspondence, 1962-1971
      - Cry California
      - Miscellany
    - Governor's Conference on Natural Beauty, 1966
    - Molera property
    - National Redwood Park
    - Urban development policy
  - Casanova, Aldo
  - Celotex Corp.
  - Century Association, New York, N.Y. (Box 20)
  - Chicago Exposition, Chicago, Ill., 1933
  - Chicago Historical Society, Chicago, Ill.
  - Committee for a More Beautiful Capital
  - Committee for Economic Development, (2 folders)
  - Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
  - Currier, Stephen R.
  - De Young exhibit, San Francisco, Calif.
  - Farr, Fred S.
  - File index (Box 21)
  - Financial and legal file
    - Corporate records
      - Accounts
      - Expenses
      - Hilton Head deposition
      - Insurance program
      - Investments
      - Isham, Lincoln, and Beale
      - Leases
      - Legal
        - Fees
        - Memoranda
      - Litigation
      - Partnership agreement
        - Certificates of limited partnership
        - Correspondence, 1940-1968
        - Miscellany
        - Printed copy of agreement (Box 22)
      - Time allocation
    - Personal records
      - Contributions
      - Divorce
      - Expenses and investments
      - Legal documents
      - Taxes (Box 23)
      - Trust fund for children
      - Wills and trusts, (2 folders)
  - Foundation for Environmental Design
  - Galante, Mrs. Clement
  - Gutheim, Frederick (Box 24)
  - Hirshhorn Museum, Washington, D.C.
  - Historic Savannah Foundation, Savannah, Ga.
  - Insurance
  - International Science Foundation, Sunnyvale, Calif.
  - Joint Center for Urban Studies of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
  - John Hancock Mutual Life Insurance Co.
  - Keep America Beautiful
  - Las Trampas, N.Mex.
    - Correspondence, 1966-1968
    - Miscellany
    - Report
  - Licenses (Box 25)
  - Mailing list
  - Mauna Kea Hotel, Hawaii
  - Memberships
  - Menus
  - Metropolitan Club, Washington, D.C.
  - Monterey, Calif.
    - Old Town
    - Planning Commission
  - Monterey coast master plan
    - Bradford, Robert B.
    - Bridges
    - Carmel Highlands Association
    - Coast Advisory Committee
    - Conservation area
    - Correspondence, 1959-1962 (Box 26)
    - Division of Highways
    - Drafts of plan
    - Ewoldsen, Hans
    - Farr, Fred S.
    - Legal aid
    - Meetings
    - Miscellany
    - Monterey Peninsula Herald
    - Printed matter
    - Reports
    - Roads, legislation (Box 27)
    - Roadside signs
    - Scenic easements
    - Scenic roads
    - Scrapbooks See Oversize, (2 vols.)
    - Sierra Club
    - Whitney, Peter D.
    - Whyte, William H.
    - Zoning
  - Monterey Peninsula Junior College, Monterey, Calif.
  - Morgan Motor Co.
  - National Academy of Design, New York, N.Y.
  - National Fund for Medical Education
  - National Geographic
  - National Council of Architectural Registration Boards
  - National Land Use Policy Committee (Box 28)
  - National Park Service
    - Advisory Board on National Parks, Historic Sites, Buildings, and Monuments
      - General file
        - 1965-1967, (3 folders)
        - 1968-1977, (4 folders) (Box 29)
      - Meetings
        - Nov. 1967-Oct. 1968, (2 folders)
        - Apr. 1969-Oct. 1970, Apr. 1976, (5 folders) (Box 30)
    - Olympic National Park, Port Angeles, Wash.
    - Sawtooth National Recreation Area, Idaho
  - National parkways
  - National Research Council
  - Nature Conservancy
  - Nepal (Box 31)
  - New-York Historical Society, New York, N.Y.
  - Open Space Advisory Committee
    - General file
    - Land program
    - Opposition
  - Operation Breakthrough, Indianapolis, Ind.
  - Owings, Nathaniel Otis
    - Correspondence, 1956-1968, (2 folders)
    - Miscellany
  - Partnership
    - Meetings
      - Committee
      - Special, Luxor, Egypt, Jan. 1967
    - Miscellany (Box 32)
  - Pennsylvania Avenue, Washington, D.C.
    - Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corp.
      - Appointment, 1973 See Oversize
      - Correspondence, 1974-1977
      - Final Environmental Impact Statement, (2 vols.)
      - Miscellany
    - President's Advisory Council on Pennsylvania Avenue (Box 33)
      - Correspondence, 1963-1964
      - Reports
    - President's Temporary Commission on Pennsylvania Avenue
      - Architecture, drafts and diagrams
      - Archives axis
      - Avenue of the Presidents
      - Capitol reflecting pool
      - Chairman's files (Box 34)
      - Conflict of interest
      - Correspondence, (3 folders)
      - Downtown progress (Box 35)
      - Expense accounts
      - Federal City Council
      - General file
        - Jan. 1964-May 1967, (2 folders)
        - June 1967-Sept. 1977 (Box 36)
      - General Services Administration
      - Goldman, Edward L., and Eleanor McPeak
      - The Grand Design
      - Johnson, Lady Bird (Box 37)
      - Joint Center for Urban Studies of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
      - Klutznick Enterprises
      - Legislation
        - Draft bills
        - Executive order no. 11210
      - Look article, Apr. 1965
      - Mailing list
      - Mall Park system
      - Meetings, 1965-1967, (5 folders) (Box 38)
      - National square
      - Newspaper clippings
      - Pennsylvania Avenue District in United States History
      - Printed matter
      - Reports
        - Periodic, (2 folders)
        - Published
        - Subcommittee on Center for Advanced Studies
      - Scrapbook See Oversize (Box 39)
      - Smithsonian Institution sculpture garden
      - Testimony before the House Interior and Insular Affairs Committee
      - The Washington Mall Master Plan See Oversize
      - Wolman building
  - Perry, Charles
  - Phelps, Lyon
  - Planning and Conservation League
  - Prestressed Concrete Institute convention, San Francisco, Calif., 6-11 Oct. 1963
  - Property
    - Carmel Highlands, Calif.
    - Leaning Wall ranch, N.Mex.
      - Correspondence, 1961-1972
      - Foundation transfer
      - Insurance (Box 40)
      - Miscellany
      - Water rights
    - "Wild Bird" estate, Big Sur, Calif.
      - Bills and receipts
      - Correspondence, 1956-1957
      - Grimes Creek
      - Miscellany
      - Utility specifications, (2 folders)
  - Reports (Box 41)
    - Activity
    - Architectural Forum Round Table
    - Miscellany
  - Ridge road controversy, Big Sur, Calif.
  - Rockefeller Foundation, New York, N.Y.
  - Roosevelt University, Chicago, Ill.
  - San Francisco, Calif.
    - Bay Area Council
    - Chamber of Commerce
    - Embarcadero Plaza
    - Market Street Development Project
    - Presidio of San Francisco
    - San Francisco Planning and Urban Renewal Association (SPUR)
      - Correspondence, 1965-1970
      - Miscellany (Box 42)
    - Save San Francisco Bay Association
    - War Memorial Opera House, (2 folders)
  - Santa Fe, N.Mex.
    - Museum of New Mexico Foundation
    - Reports
  - Save the Redwoods League
  - Save the Sea Otter
  - Seattle, Wash., Civic Center Foundation competition
  - Shimba Hills National Wildlife Park, Kenya
  - Sierra Club (Box 43)
  - Skidmore, Louis
  - Standard Insurance Co.
  - Stevenson (Adlai) Memorial Fund
  - Syracuse University, Syracuse, N.Y.
  - Tennessee Gas Transmission Co.
  - Time article, 2 Aug. 1968
  - Trips, 1960-1965, (6 folders) (Box 44)
  - Udall, Stewart L.
  - University of California Planning Conference, Berkeley, Calif.
  - Work Ranch, Monterey, Calif.
- Speeches and Writings File, 1944-1977 (Box 44-56)
  Drafts of speeches and writings, correspondence, printed copies, galley proofs, production material, research material, notes, and miscellaneous items relating to Owings's articles, books, lectures, and speeches.
  Arranged by type of material and chronologically thereunder.
  - Articles (Box 44)
    - Correspondence
    - 1944, 10 Dec., "Comments on Lighting Layout and Design," Illuminating Engineering
    - 1945, May, "How Little Traverse Hospital Met Unique Expansion Problems," Hospital Management
    - 1948
      - Jan., "A Radically New Conception of Tomorrow's Office Building," National Real Estate and Building
        - Journal
      - Mar., "Basic Considerations in Hospital Design," Modern Hospital
    - 1962, Feb., "Two Looks at Preservation," AIA Journal
    - 1966
      - May, "Skidmore, Owings, and Merrill: An Architectural Community," Engineering News-Record
      - Nov., Sports Illustrated article
    - 1967
      - Apr., "Urban Transportation Planning Concepts," Traffic Quarterly
      - Fall, "Core Cities: Their Future," Per/Se
    - 1969, Dec.
      - AIA Journal article
      - Christian Science Monitor article
    - 1970
      - July/Aug., "Las Trampas: A Past Resurrected," New Mexico
      - Aug., "Mass Transit and the Cities," Current History (Box 45)
    - 1971, "Man and His Environment," Outlook
    - 1972, Spring, "The City: Go Slow, Go Slow ...," Cry California
    - 1973, 1 Apr., "The Despair of Nat Owings," California Living Magazine
    - 1974, 11 Mar., "Construction Management," Daily Pacific Builder
    - 1977, "Emphasis," Sunstone Review
  - Books
    - The American Aesthetic (1969)
      - Contracts
      - Correspondence, 1965-1970, (4 folders)
      - Drafts
      - Galley Proofs (Box 46)
      - Layout See Oversize (Box 47)
      - Miscellany
      - Photographic proofs See Oversize
      - Production materials, (2 folders)
      - Production materials, (2 vols.) (Box 48)
      - Scrapbook See Oversize (Box 49)
    - "Made in America"
      - Drafts
      - Manuscript copy
    - Spaces in Between: An Architect's Journey (1973)
      - Correspondence
        - 1969-1971
        - 1972-1974 (Box 50)
      - Drafts
        - Chapters, (3 folders)
        - Miscellany (Box 51)
      - Japanese edition
      - Miscellany
      - Research material
      - Reviews
  - Lectures
    - 1962
      - Salzburg, Austria
        - Correspondence
          - 1962, (2 folders)
          - 1963-1972 (Box 52)
        - Lectures
    - 1966
      - London, England
        - Backup material
        - Correspondence
        - Lectures, (2 folders)
        - Miscellany (Box 53)
    - 1973-1974
      - Ball State University, Muncie, Ind.
  - Speeches
    - Correspondence
    - Notes
    - 1946, 15 Oct., Wayfarers' Club, Chicago, Ill.
    - 1957, 30 July, World Conference on Prestressed Concrete
    - 1959
      - 27 May, San Francisco Museum of Art, San Francisco, Calif.
      - 12 June, Chadwick School
    - 1960, 20 Oct., University Associates, Kansas City, Mo.
    - 1961, 14 Oct., National Trust for Historic Preservation, New York, N.Y.
    - 1962
      - 4 June, Jefferson City, Mo.
      - 13 June, National Association of Building Owners and Managers, San Francisco, Calif.
    - 1963
      - 1 May, Contra Costa Board of Supervisors, Concord, Calif.
      - 11 Sept., Williamsburg, Va.
    - 1964
      - 7 Apr., Senate Advisory Committee on a Master Plan for Scenic Highways, Washington, D.C.